<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grand catastrophe, or The change of government: being a vvord about the last turn of these times written in a letter to a friend, as an essay, either to give, or to receive satisfaction in the dispute of the last change. By one who takes leave to stile himself Johannes Cornubiensis.</title>
            <author>Cornubiensis, Johannes.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1488</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E726_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206800</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865906</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865906</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118160</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85517)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118160)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E726[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grand catastrophe, or The change of government: being a vvord about the last turn of these times written in a letter to a friend, as an essay, either to give, or to receive satisfaction in the dispute of the last change. By one who takes leave to stile himself Johannes Cornubiensis.</title>
                  <author>Cornubiensis, Johannes.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.I. and are to bee sold at the Crown in Popes-head-Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 18 1653"; the 4 in the imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118160:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Grand Cataſtrophe, OR THE Change of Government: BEING A VVord about the laſt turn of theſe Times WRITTEN In a Letter to a Friend, as an Eſſay, either to give, or to receive Satisfaction in the Diſpute of the laſt CHANGE. By one who takes leave to ſtile himſelf Johannes Cornubienſis..</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 75.7.</bibl>
               <p>God is Judge, Hee putteth down one and ſetteth up another.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 29.2.</bibl>
               <p>When the Righteous are in authority the people rejoyce; but when the wicked beareth rule, the people mourn.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by R. I. and are to bee ſold at the Crown in Popeſ-head-Alley. 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118160:2"/>
            <head>The Grand Cataſtrophe, or the change of Government, being a word about the laſt turne of theſe times.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat ſaying of the Pſalmiſt hath of late times oft been in my thoughts, even that; <hi>Thy way is in the ſea, and thy path in the mighty waters, and thy foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps are not known,</hi> Pſal. 77.19. For if ever there were an Age ſince <hi>Iſraels</hi> advance out of <hi>Aepypt,</hi> when God once and againe made <hi>his path in the waters</hi> (litterally at <hi>Jordan</hi>) and had his <hi>way through the Sea</hi> (even the red Sea) and through the whole of that miraculous providence was, <hi>as a ſhip in the ſea,</hi> whoſe way and footſteps are unknown; If ever (I ſay ſince that age) God hath ſo acted again the ſecond time, to bring up his people from an Aegypt, ſure it hath been in this, which we have ſeen. And indeed the works of God in the midſt of us have been ſo <hi>parallel</hi> unto thoſe <hi>paſt providences,</hi> as that I have often ſaid, they have been but another <hi>edition</hi> of them with ſome <hi>inlargements.</hi> Our way out of Bondage, and through the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath been ſo like, that ſcarce can there be mentioned any particular act then, which (as <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> phraſe is) <hi>hath not its mate now.</hi> What God hath done for the by-paſt time, there is ſcarce any ſo great a ſtranger in <hi>Iſrael</hi> but can tell, but what God is doing, or will doe, is that which poſeth the greateſt Teachers in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and I had almoſt ſaid, we ſee <hi>not our ſignes, there is no more any Prophet, neither is there among us any that knoweth how long.</hi> That great <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>concurring deſires, and prayers, and counſels of the godly</hi> (which was wont never to faile us) is now eclipſed by thoſe ſad divided aimes, and ſub-divided thoughts, which cauſe breaking, and bleeding of heart every where; and how long it wil be ere the <hi>envie of Ephraim</hi> (the major, or ten parts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors) and the <hi>envie of Judah</hi> (the minor, or two parts of them) ſhal depart, and each ſhal not vexe, or vary one from another,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118160:3"/>who can tell? yet certaine the time ſhal come, when it ſhal be; but in the interim, to ſee through theſe clouds, to be able to heare the voyce of the <hi>Father</hi> in the midſt of the confuſed noyſe of his <hi>Children,</hi> is the great deſire, and indeavour of my ſoule. And that I might <hi>pump</hi> up the deeper, and fuller diſcoveries of longer heads and hearts then my owne, I will adventure humbly to caſt in a <hi>diſh of water</hi> out of my little ciſterne-thus: I have for ſome yeares eyed that place of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 23, 24, 25, 26. as a Propheſie, which is yet to receive its accompliſhment. And much hath been (as I humbly judge) done in the midſt of us, as to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory or threatning part of it; whether God be not about to enter (at leaſt) upon the more poſitive mercy of it, I would a little inquire; and let that ver. 26. be the baſis of the inquiry, the words are thus; <hi>I will reſtore thy Judges as at the firſt, and thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors as at the beginning, afterward thou ſhalt be called the city of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, the faithfull city.</hi> From this Propheſie I would ſpeake the words of truth with ſoberneſſe; and oh, that the ſons of truth and ſoberneſſe others I deſire not to deal withall) would give me an anſwer, that if I erre I might ſee it, for verily I am unwilling my errour ſhould abide with me; teach me, and I wil hold my tongue, and cauſe me to underſtand wherein I have erred.</p>
            <p>But yet heare me of your goodneſſe (yee Judges and Princes of reaſon) while in a few words I acquaint yee with my thoughts, about this Scripture in reference to theſe times.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>I have thought that God clearly intimates a reſolve</hi> (as it were upon the debate) <hi>to change the forme of Government from what it was now,</hi> (corrupted by Kings and Princes) <hi>unto what it was better, when adminiſtred in the dayes of the Judges and Elders</hi> (or as it is here phraſed) Counſellours, Kings and Princes of a Monarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal principle, and power, were not <hi>ab initio,</hi> i. e. not from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning amongſt his people, they were indeed at <hi>laſt,</hi> but not at <hi>firſt.</hi> Now tel me (for I deſire to learn) if the context of theſe words, joyned with the words themſelves ſpeake not, as if God would raiſe up an expectation of ſuch a change, as in which he would remove <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> (whom he cals <hi>rebellious, and companions of Theeves</hi>) as his <hi>enemies,</hi> and adverſaries, as thoſe which had made the faithful City (<hi>Iſraels</hi> Common-wealth) an <hi>Harlot;</hi> and which that it might become againe the <hi>city of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118160:3"/>ſhould be bleſſed with its firſt Government of <hi>Judges and Counſellours.</hi> After all Diſpute and Comment (which yet I have had the advantage to heare and read) upon that, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. it appeares clearly, that at <hi>the firſt,</hi> and in the <hi>beginning,</hi> God did diſ-approve of the change of Government from <hi>Judges</hi> to <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there ſpoke of, was to terrifie his people from their deſire, it being directly oppoſite to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The manner of Kingly Government was, and hath been experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced, to be no more like Gods, then the violent, tyranical ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Reboboams</hi> young Counſellours, unto the grave and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Counſel which the ancient men gave, who were indeed the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, and adviſed better then young Lads did; yet ſtill it hath been the manner of Monarchy to act after the <hi>young mens Councel,</hi> and not according to the councel of the aged. As thereby ſhewing it ſelfe to be not the government of the <hi>beginning,</hi> nor that which was at <hi>firſt.</hi> But God ſpeaking here of reducing the ſtate of things to that <hi>prime</hi> patterne, doth (to me at leaſt) clearly intimate this change of Government, which we have had ſome experience of, and which others ſhal in time finde; for we are but as the firſt ripe fruit to that Harveſt, wherein the ſickle of Providence ſhal be put into the Kingdomes of men, to accompliſh this Prophecie, of Gods cutting downe Monarchs, his Adverſaries, and making way for reſtoring of his <hi>Judges as at firſt, and his Counſellours as at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, may it not then be thought <hi>to be</hi> (not to ſay impious, but) <hi>very impolitique, and imprudent in any people or perſon to dote up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and admire that which the great God of all the World is reſolved to pull downe.</hi> Certainly, it's the Creatures folly to reſiſt the Creators counſel, who ever ſet himſelfe either in deſire, or deſigne againſt the Lord, and did receive the one, or accompliſh the other; without doubt, if the <hi>moſt high</hi> rule in the <hi>Kingdomes of men,</hi> and doe whatſoever he pleaſeth, there can be no reſiſting of his wil. I am apt to thinke, that the time haſtens in which God wil make all the Princes of the earth (<hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>-like) to graze with the Beaſts, and to wander in the Wilderneſſe, that they may ſee, and know, and underſtand, and conſider that he is reſolved to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118160:4"/>deale with them as rebels; and that their power, and pride, and pomp ſhal be ſo ſtained, as that all their blood in their owne, and vaſſels veines, ſhal never be able to recover their ſplendor any more. <hi>Whatſoever God will in Heaven, or Earth, that does he.</hi> And though Monarchy lift up it ſelf above the Skies, though it fixe it ſelfe amongſt the Starres, yet even thence ſhal it tumble down, by that power which diſſolves the Hoſt of Heaven, and cauſeth the Stars to fall as the leaves from the Vine; and ſith this appears to be his determined purpoſe upon the whole Earth, I perſwade my ſelfe it wil be but <hi>a vaine thing,</hi> for the Kings of the earth, and the Princes to take councel together, to reſiſt the Lord, and his Chriſt; ſurely when he ſtrikes they'le be but as a <hi>Potters veſſel,</hi> and when God is breaking of them, why ſhould not they be to us as a <hi>veſſel wherein there is no pleaſure.</hi> Nay, why rather ſhould not all entertaine with delight the change which God is about to make, ſince it is from the <hi>worſe</hi> to the <hi>better,</hi> from the unrighteous, and tyrannous power of <hi>Monarchies and Princes,</hi> into his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Counſellours,</hi> which were from the beginning, which indeed were the <hi>firſt,</hi> and ſhal be <hi>laſt</hi> in this world, till <hi>David</hi> himſelfe doe come againe, and the <hi>Lord Chriſt be exalted in his day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it hath been in my thoughts to conſider, <hi>whether this Propheſie hath received its accompliſhment;</hi> or be yet to be fulfilled; Though ſome Expoſitors ſeem to be confident of the paſt imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the already fulfilling of this Propheſie, yet many doubt it. True it is, that there was a <hi>Tanquam-accompliſhing</hi> of this Prediction, after the returne of the <hi>Jewes</hi> from the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> captivity, but yet I cannot be convinced (at preſent) that then there was a <hi>total accompliſhment</hi> of it, ſo as to reſt therein, and to expect no more from this Scripture; for let it be conſidered, whether ever after that returne (ever in their beſt and quieteſt eſtate) <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were ſo ordered and eſtabliſhed, as that it might in the fulneſſe of the Letter, and in the whole latitude of the intendment of the phraſe, be called, <hi>the city of righteouſneſſe, the faithfull city;</hi> certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſacred word wil not give my faith a footing to beleeve it. <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> in their workes, and writings, ſpeake at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rate, <hi>Nehemiah</hi> conteſts about Oppreſſion, which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them rife and ridged (and that in the prime of their refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118160:4"/>and returne) makes me thinke then their ſtate did not deſerve the glory of being called, <hi>The city of righteouſneſſe;</hi> and the poſture, or rather prepoſterous, and diſorderly ſtate of affaires, which ſome yeares after he found at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> doth give little ground to call it all that time <hi>the faithfull citie,</hi> &amp;c. This makes me to think, that this Propheſie is but <hi>parallel</hi> to that of <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 31.23 and therefore it received not its accompliſhment at their returne from <hi>Babylon,</hi> but is to be fulfilled when God ſhall bring them up, and back from the <hi>North,</hi> when not only <hi>Judah,</hi> the two Tribes, (which alone returned from <hi>Babylon</hi>) but likewiſe <hi>Iſrael</hi> (the ten Tribes) with them ſhould rejoyce in that Government of <hi>Judges and Counſellours</hi> as at firſt, until they come to their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome-ſtate under the reigne of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> their King. And in caſe there were a fulfilling of this Propheſie after their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne from <hi>Babylon,</hi> I am apt to thinke it was but ſuch a fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling as hath been of ſome others, which was rather <hi>in part,</hi> and <hi>in aſſurance of the truth, then in whole and full perfection of the Propheſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſuppoſing then this Propheſie as yet not to be fulfilled, <hi>Why may not the Iſles of the Gentiles as well looke after, and expect the fulfilling of it amongſt them</hi> (I ſay) <hi>as well as the remnant of the Jewes?</hi> Is God only the God of <hi>Jewes,</hi> or is he not equally the God of the <hi>Gentiles?</hi> In the Propheſie of Gods reſtoring and ſetting judgement in the earth, are not the <hi>Gentiles</hi> expreſly mentioned to ſhare therein? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. And are not they ſaid to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, <hi>waiting for his Law?</hi> Nay, doth not the connexion of this, and the next chapter import, that this Propheſie relates to the times of the Nations flowing into the light, and Law of the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias? certaine I am, the Rabbins (who uſe to make advantage of all Scriptures, to the utmoſt for their owne Nation, and are not favourers of us ſinners of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) doe underſtand this Scripture of the times of the Meſſiah, who ſhal prevaile over the wicked (ſo <hi>Kimchies</hi> phraſe is for us <hi>Gentiles</hi>) And clear it is that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> are promiſed (and ſo Propheſied of) <hi>to partake with, to ſhare in, and ſuck of the ſame breaſts of conſolation with the Jewes;</hi> now whether it be a conſolation to have good Judges, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Counſellours (as <hi>Iſrael had at the firſt, and in the beginning</hi>) let thoſe ſpeake who have felt the burthen, and taſted the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118160:5"/>of the tyranny of <hi>rebellious Princes and Monarchs.</hi> Since then this Promiſe, or Propheſie (call it as we pleaſe) referres to the <hi>Jewes</hi> expreſly, as a mercy to come in its ſeaſon, let us not bind our ſelves with the cords of feare, and diffidence from coming in to participate with them in the ſame, for as much as we are now <hi>of the ſame body, and fellow heires of the ſame hopes, and partners in the ſame promiſes with them</hi> (that being deſtroyed which made the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) Neither let it be thought too <hi>great</hi> ambition for us <hi>Gentiles</hi> to <hi>precede</hi> them in the injoying of thoſe Propheſies, ſince we doe goe before them in greater matters. And why may not God hereby provoke the <hi>Jewes</hi> to jealouſie and emulation, when they ſhal ſee us to love and enjoy what once they had, &amp; as yet want; and yet this wil not hinder, but that the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſhal have in time a <hi>gradual</hi> (though not ſpecificall) <hi>preheminence</hi> above us the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles;</hi> for albeit we be the <hi>firſt</hi> in the injoyment of the fulfilling, yet may they be the <hi>chiefe</hi> in the perfection of this promiſed mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; though they come in <hi>laſt,</hi> yet may they be advanced to <hi>higheſt</hi> place, and ſo <hi>the firſt ſhal be laſt, and the last ſhall be first;</hi> they <hi>the firſt in the Promiſe, laſt in the performance;</hi> we the <hi>laſt, firſt</hi> in the fulfilling, and yet they the <hi>last,</hi> come up to be the <hi>chiefe</hi> in the injoyment: And ſo Chriſt, who is firſt our ſalvation and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement, may yet <hi>be the glory of his people Iſrael in both,</hi> ſending and ſetling amongſt us his <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Counſellours,</hi> till himſelfe alone ſhal come to ſit upon the Throne of his father <hi>David,</hi> that by us, as by a <hi>light,</hi> may be ſeen what ſhal be the glory of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and ſo the final advantage of the <hi>Jew</hi> above the <hi>Gentile,</hi> ſhal be <hi>much every way,</hi> when they ſhal (though <hi>laſt,</hi> and <hi>after</hi> us) enjoy their Judges as at <hi>firſt, and their Counſellours as in the beginning,</hi> in a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as farre exceeding us, as that of <hi>Rachel</hi> the younger, did that of <hi>Leah</hi> the elder, and ſo they be the <hi>prime</hi> in beauty, though we the <hi>firſt</hi> in <hi>birth,</hi> or beginning of this Propheſie.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, in caſe theſe things be thus, let us a little conſider <hi>what is this Government of Judges and Counſellours, which upon the change of Government we may expect, and ſhould acquieſce in, as a mercy promiſed.</hi> And here it muſt be promiſed as an indubitable conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>That the government of Judges was but of one Perſon, as chiefe Judge,</hi> at one <hi>time.</hi> The great ſpace of time after the diviſion of <hi>Canaan</hi> by Lot (which is the Epocha from which the giving and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118160:5"/>governing of Judges is reckoned, as <hi>Acts</hi> 13.19. &amp; 20. compared with <hi>Judges</hi> 3.9.) had its courſe in the ſucceſſion of Judges, one after another, and in all that time there were never more then one <hi>Judge</hi> at a time. The Government is expreſſed in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of <hi>Judges,</hi> by reaſon of their ſucceſſive turnes, one after the death of another, and not becauſe there ſhould be, or were many at once. Conſult the Book of the <hi>Judges,</hi> and you will not in the leaſt heſitate herein; <hi>Othoniel, Elon, Deborah, Gideon,</hi> and the reſt governed, or judged by turnes (during the time of their lives) and not any two of them at one time.</p>
            <p>This being cleare beyond contradiction, conſider we a little the <hi>uſe of the Judge at any time,</hi> what it was for, and upon which any came to that place; and conſider we the rule and power of a Judge ſo inabled; Now as for his riſe; <hi>It is evident it was upon a Martiall or Military account,</hi> he that was the <hi>deliverer</hi> was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and thereupon the <hi>Judge;</hi> the perſon which providence rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the time of any of their ſtreights to deliver them out of the hand of their enemies, was (<hi>Eo nomine, eadem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione</hi>) the <hi>Judge</hi> afterward, during terme of life; <hi>Jephtah</hi> therefore did upon theſe termes covenant to undertake the Office of being their <hi>Generall in Warre,</hi> that he might be their <hi>Judge in peace.</hi> Had not the people promiſed that, and called God to witneſſe (as the ſeale and ſecurity of that Promiſe) he had not gone forth either againſt the malignant <hi>Ammonites</hi> firſt, of the male-contented <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraimites</hi> afterward, but being aſſured of being <hi>Judge</hi> after the warre, he ingaged in the warre, and according to the ingagement of the Elders unto him, he judged (or governed as chiefe) ſixe yeares afterward; upon whoſe death <hi>Ibzan</hi> ſucceeded him in the Judicature of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and judged ſeven yeares, even till he dyed. Now albeit it appeares not by the ſacred Hiſtory what was the ground upon which the Judge (for the time being) was elected in time of peace; (for neither in the dayes of <hi>Elon,</hi> who ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Ibzan</hi>) nor of <hi>Abdaon</hi> (who came to be Judge after <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> was there any vvars) albeit (I ſay) therefore it appeare not what was the particular <hi>worth,</hi> or <hi>merit, eminency,</hi> or <hi>deſert,</hi> for which the election in thoſe times was made, yet ſtill it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that in <hi>times of warre,</hi> and ſtreights, the valiant and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful management of the affaires then, was alway the ground which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118160:6"/>gave the riſe and reaſon of the particular election unto the power and honour of the chief Judicature afterward.</p>
            <p>Having paſſed thus farre in our inquiry, let us now conſider <hi>whether or no that during this government of Judges, there was not alſo annexed unto it, the Synedrian of the Elders, and ſo at the ſame time there was the J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DGE,</hi> and the <hi>COVNSELLOVRS,</hi> as having an hand in, and authority with the Judge to manage the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And there are (beſides many conjecturall evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences) three things, which may be of weight and ſufficiency to atteſt, and carry us to plenary beleife hereof.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That no Hiſtory, either ſacred or prophane doth (or can) make it appeare, That from the firſt inſtitution, or foundation of the Synedrian (which was by Moſes) there was not an abolition or diſſolving of that power which they had, and exerciſed in the Government of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Cunaeus</hi> is cleare and poſitive in this, his words are, <hi>Id concilium cum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum a Moſe eſſet ſemper deinde ſub judicibus, regibuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficibus uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad extremam Judaeae deſolationem fuit manſit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp;c.</hi> neither have I as yet met with any Author of name or note (indeed with none at all) that ever denied this, but that ſtill during the time of <hi>Judges</hi> (as afterwards) there were alſo the <hi>Counſellours</hi> (the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty Elders) who did alway manage the affaires of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eſpeciall in Civil things, as in matters of Fact and fault between man and man, throughout all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>The frequent mention of the Elders in the Booke of Judges is ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious that it muſt be granted, that even in that time the Elders were.</hi> And that they were of power appeares cleare enough, both by their calling of <hi>Jeptath</hi> to be <hi>Generall</hi> of their Forces, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanting with him that he ſhould be <hi>Judge</hi> upon his ſucceſſe, <hi>Judg.</hi> 11.9, 10. And why ſhould it be doubted or queſtioned, whether or no this conjunction of <hi>Judges</hi> and <hi>Counſellours</hi> were together at <hi>Mizpeh</hi> at that time, when as its conſtitution was but yet new, and nothing appeares why it ſhould be thought either to be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or abrogated.</p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>The particular ſtory of the Levite and his Concubine is of evidence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough by it ſelf to conſtrain us to conclude, that there were Counſellours in the times of the Judges;</hi> To whom but to the Elders did he addreſſe himſelfe? Who but they did do him juſtice? indeed in thoſe days there was no <hi>Judge in Iſrael</hi> (as there was not at ſome other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118160:6"/>times) but yet it appeares then there were theſe <hi>Counſellours;</hi> and a very ſtrong argument it is that they were, <hi>when and while there were Judges,</hi> becauſe they were when there were none. In <hi>Jeph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabs</hi> caſe they elected him <hi>Generall,</hi> and conſtituted him <hi>Judge;</hi> and now in the <hi>Levites caſe,</hi> they heare his in jury, and doe him Juſtice. Beſides, had there been a <hi>Judge</hi> at that time in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> its queſtionable whether or no the complaint ſhould have been made to him, unleſſe the extraordinarineſs of the caſe had made him to take cognizance of it, for <hi>in Civil affaires</hi> (as one wel obſerves) the Judges did but <hi>rarely appeare,</hi> and <hi>when is was, the occaſion or affaire was weekly;</hi> Upon all this it wil appeare, That <hi>indeed the Government by Judges was mixed with the Synedrian of Elders,</hi> and Judges and Counſellours were Gods Government at <hi>firſt,</hi> or the kinde of power and rule by which <hi>Iſrael</hi> was governed <hi>at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> ſo that this will be the reſult of the inquiry; that God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing here to give his people their <hi>Judges as at firſt, and their Counſellours as at the beginning:</hi> The Government which hereupon we are to expect, is, that <hi>forme which the people of God had at firſt, when they were poſſeſſed of the Land of</hi> Canaan, <hi>and were governed by Judges and Elders.</hi> And the reaſon why this was called the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment <hi>as at the firſt, and as in the beginning,</hi> is, becauſe that this was the <hi>firſt forme,</hi> or way of rule which the <hi>Jews</hi> had after the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Nations of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> were deſtroyed, and that Land was divided, and injoyed by Lot; till which time indeed they had not <hi>Judges,</hi> i. e. not that Government, as <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.19, 20. Nor were they capable till then of any ſetled forme of Government, becauſe till then they were not <hi>a ſetled Common-wealth; Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> were their Leaders from a ſtrange Land, and their Deliverers till they came unto <hi>Canaan,</hi> and they guided, and governed them in their march, and military con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; but when afterward they were ſetled, and had their Land divided by Lot, then God gave them Judges; till then their ſtate was but <hi>itinerant,</hi> and unſetled; but from that time they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a Common-wealth, and (though not freed from warres, yet) were ſetled where they were to abide, and therefore this was <hi>their firſt,</hi> and <hi>beginning eſtate,</hi> the prime conſtitution of that Common-wealth. Then (Reader) that I may apply this to our preſent time, let me expoſtulate the caſe with male-content, or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118160:7"/>diſſatisfied perſons about the late, ſtrange, and unexpected turne that hath been amongſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why may we not rather rejoyce, and reſt in it as in a mercy Propheſied, than murmure at it, and ſlander it as being a deſigne plotted?</hi> Or if we ſhould grant it a thing <hi>plotted by men,</hi> why may we not rejoyce, that God by men hath accompliſhed his owne intentions, <hi>howbeit</hi> (Aſſyrian like) <hi>they neither meant ſo, nor did their hearts think ſo?</hi> Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly though the wrath, or pride of men doe not directly aime at, nor can therefore groundedly expect to accompliſh the righteouſneſs of God; yet we have often ſeene, (and of late have had many choyſe experiences of it) that when, or where man did but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, and appoint tranſactions to ſuch, or ſuch an end, God did over-rule and order them unto the fulfilling of his owne purpoſes. <hi>Doe yee not remember the former things? &amp;c. Have yee forgot the dayes of old?</hi> when neceſſity conſtrained us, both in Parliament and Army to reſolve, and doe things, ſtrange, and ſeemingly ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centrick, which albeit they ſtartled us at firſt, nor were intended for that end (which yet was the bleſſed iſſue of them) have yet been ſuch as we have had cauſe to ſay, <hi>What hath God done for us, and how came he downe by terrible things which we looked not for, doing and accompliſhing the counſels and purpoſes of his owne will, which</hi> we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>did</hi> (at firſt at leaſt) <hi>expect,</hi> may not it be ſo then now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? and upon the Premiſes may not we conclude this, as the fruit of our laſt change; <hi>That God is now about to give us the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his people, and the fulfilling of a propheſie:</hi> for verily a <hi>Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, and Counſellors</hi> (eſpecially thoſe of the Grand Synedrian in Triennial Parliament) is much like <hi>Iſraels Judges at the firſt, and their Counſellors at the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> No, but <hi>this is more like a King and his Lords;</hi> its more like that which we have fought and prayed againſt, then like that which we have deſired and expected.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But <hi>are you not miſtaken in your ſelves? or were you not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided in your aymes?</hi> Did you, or durſt you pray, or fight for any thing inconſiſtent with, or oppoſite to any thing Propheſied of, or promiſed in the Scriptures of truth? <hi>And is not one ſingle perſon aſſiſted by a Councel, and concluded by, yea and reſponſible to a Syne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian of Elders</hi> (Heads of our Tribes in Parliament) I ſay, is not this <hi>like Judges</hi> of old, and Counſellours at the beginning.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118160:7"/>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But a Protector is but one ſingle perſon, and God ſpeakes of Judges,</hi> and ſo it is Monarchy, and not that, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>It is a miſtake</hi> (as hath been hinted) to <hi>thinke there were more Judges then one at a time.</hi> Though the expreſſion in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie be <hi>plural,</hi> yet the power and place in the exerciſe of it was <hi>ſingle;</hi> and therefore though it be called the time when the <hi>Judges ruled</hi> (as <hi>Ruth</hi> 1.1.) yet was there but one Judge, who judged at a time. One <hi>Jephtah,</hi> one <hi>Tola, &amp;c.</hi> and no more. Beſides, it is <hi>a groſſe miſtake to thinke, and ſay, that this is a Monarchicall, or Kingly Government, and that hereby the Act, and Declaration for the aboliſhing of Kingly power is tranſgreſſed;</hi> for know and conſider, <hi>It is one thing to be governed by one, and another thing to be governed by a Monarch;</hi> though every Monarch be <hi>one,</hi> yet <hi>every ſingle</hi> one is not a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. The Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> is but <hi>one,</hi> yet no <hi>Monarch;</hi> the State holden in <hi>Holland</hi> was but one, yet no <hi>King;</hi> the <hi>Judges</hi> (for the time being) were but one at a time, yet no <hi>Kings.</hi> It is true, in the time of their interval it is ſaid, <hi>Then was there no King in Iſrael;</hi> but that was rather from the general uſe of the word King, then from their power, or rule as Kings; and this will appeare evidently by two things (beſides that all Authors do ſpecifically diſtinguiſh the times of that Government of Kings and Judges, which they could not, in caſe they were the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>The People when they deſired a King in oppoſition to</hi> Samuel, <hi>who was the laſt Judge, did certainly know that there was a very cleare and vaſt difference between a Judge and a King;</hi> otherwiſe they would not have deſired, and conteſted for that which they had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>God himſelfe when he ſpeakes of that buſineſſe, doth more then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate what a difference there would be between the perſons and powers of Kings which they deſired, and Judges which they had;</hi> ſo that to ſay, that a <hi>King,</hi> and a <hi>Judge,</hi> (or <hi>Protector,</hi> being no more then a <hi>Judge</hi>) is all one, bids very faire, and goes very facre to cleare the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from ſin, in their deſire of a <hi>King,</hi> and to charge God with <hi>folly,</hi> that he was ſo offended with them, when they deſired no more in effect then his owne promiſe of Judges. Adde to this, that God in this place of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> doth oppoſe <hi>his Judges and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours</hi> to <hi>Kings and Princes,</hi> the government of the one, unto the government of the other, which had they not been <hi>divers</hi> need
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118160:8"/>not be; for God might have ſaid, <hi>I will deſtroy Kings and Princes my enemies, and give them my Kings and Princes;</hi> No, but ile give my <hi>Judges</hi> inſtead of thoſe <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true indeed, <hi>Joſephus</hi> cals the Judges in Greek <hi>Monarchs,</hi> and the Hebrew in <hi>Judges</hi> once and againe ſtiles them <hi>Melecks;</hi> but it is becauſe of the more lax ſignification of the words, and not becauſe of the ſtrict acceptation of the thing, and the knowne and now frequent notion of Kings and Monarchs, The <hi>Roman</hi> Dictators, <hi>Cinna, Sylla, (Mario)</hi> &amp;c. where by the Greek Writers ſtiled <hi>Monarchs,</hi> and yet it is known they were not Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, as the thing ſtrictly ſignifies. The Dictators were but (if I may ſay ſo) Protectors <hi>pro tempore;</hi> the wiſe <hi>Tacitus,</hi> (and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all Hiſtorians of note) diſtinguiſh betweene the Dictators and <hi>Caeſars,</hi> as between two kinds of Government.</p>
            <p>It is not <hi>a ſingle perſon,</hi> but <hi>a ſole power</hi> which makes a Monarch ſo called, and known, and this the late King knew very well, when upon diſcourſes of a limited Prerogative, he was wont to ſay; <hi>It was but a deſigne to unking him, and make him another Duke of Venice, SOLENES OF POWER, SOVERAIGNTY OF RVLE, HEREDITARINESSE OF</hi> Title, <hi>IMSPONCI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLENES OF ACTION,</hi> &amp;c. have been deemed, and urged as the <hi>Regalia of a Monarch,</hi> and when theſe are not, the Maſters of Monarchy will tell you, Kingſhip is <hi>wanting,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>waning,</hi> and in its decay.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But how ſoone may the Protector aſſume this if he pleaſe, and what abſolute power hath he at preſent, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>Have we ground to thinke him a man of ſo much ambition, and ſo little faith, as to violate his Oath, though for a Kingdome?</hi> Hath not the Nation had experiments ſtrong and ſincere, long enough to daſh ſuch jealous Brats in peeces? For which of his good works is it that you thus ſuſpect him?</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But he is but a man,</hi> and temptations may overcome, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Reply. <hi>Let this rather fill your ſoule with prayers, then foment in you jealouſies.</hi> But is not he bounded? Are not the Articles of agreement, like the bounds of the Sea, ſuch as if he would <hi>rage</hi> he cannot paſſe? And whatſoever power he hath at preſent, may not the next Parliament leſſen it? And his preſent Councel check it; for how little a part of power hath he without the adviſe and conſent of his Councel.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118160:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But <hi>yet he hath the ſword,</hi> and may breake out, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Anſ. <hi>Yet ſtill we have jealouſie,</hi> and ſo make feare without grounds. <hi>Is there no fidelity in the preſent</hi> Councel? <hi>Is there no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesty in the Officers of the Army</hi> to reſtraine, and oppreſſe extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies? Or; <hi>is there no power in Prayer, no God in Heaven to mend all?</hi> verily if the Protector ſhould fal from <hi>grace</hi> (which yet I am not ſo much an <hi>Arminian</hi> as to feare) and ſhould either miſuſe, and miſ-improve his power to ſelfe power, and pride, &amp;c. all that feare God, would cry out, <hi>let him be accurſed,</hi> and I ſhould thinke my ſelfe worthy to ſhare in the curſe, if I ſhould not ſay, <hi>Amen,</hi> even ſo be it Lord. <hi>Let him be the ſhame of men, the ſcorne of State, the abborrency of all that feare God, if be make his Protectorſhip a ſtep to Kingſhip for himſelfe or his.</hi> And here let me take the liberty to ſay, I could heartily wiſh, and upon my knees humbly begge, that (as an addition unto that Article, <hi>that the Protector ſhall not be hereditary</hi>) it might be annexed, <hi>that the Family of any one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector ſhall be wholly cut off from being elected to the Protectorſhip, at leaſt unto the third Generation.</hi> It would be a <hi>teſt of ſingular ſincerity</hi> in the now Lord Protector, to procure ſuch an addition, and it would be <hi>a great ſecurity to prevent Monarchy,</hi> or other evil which may ariſe out of this office. We know, how that the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> is not <hi>hereditary</hi> fundamentally, but <hi>Elective,</hi> yet for want of ſuch a caution, as I humbly motion, how long the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> hath perpetuated the Imperiall power, in its owne Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, to the grand injury of all <hi>Germany,</hi> is a thing that needs no Hiſtory to confirme, or ſet forth. I have heard (I confeſſe) that many have ſaid, and doe ſay, that there is a long line of pedigree drawne up, <hi>to prove the Lord Protector to be lineally deſcended from Cadwallador;</hi> and this hath been, and is ſtill made uſe of by ſome, to inſinuate a deſign, a <hi>future Kingſhip</hi> for himſelfe, or his; but as I know no juſt ground for to beleeve the truth of this ſurmiſe, ſo I perſwade my ſelfe, his Highneſſe the Protector, is <hi>more Christian, and leſſe Welch-man,</hi> then to minde ſuch fooliſh vaine Pedegrees; if he draw not his line from Chriſt he will not be Honourable in the eyes of God, or Saints; and <hi>I hope his converſation will fully prove this report a lye.</hi> Neither doe I doubt in the leaſt that he will venter the perill of life and perjury upon ſo meane an account,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118160:9"/>as an antiquated (that I ſay not abominated) peece of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldry.</p>
            <p>There is alſo another <hi>idle report,</hi> which yet becauſe its handed as from a <hi>Knight,</hi> and <hi>a Biſhop,</hi> ile hint in a word, and ſpeake ſhortly unto. The report is; <hi>That a Knight</hi> (whether errant or otherwiſe) <hi>having little to doe at Bath, ſhould ſearch for annoſities in the Cathedrall there, and at laſt found a certaine Story, which it ſeemes was</hi> Jothams <hi>Apologue, painted and verſified;</hi> and that this ſhould be one line in the Poetry, BUT WOE TO US WHEN OLIVER SHALL BE KING. Hereupon it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and concluded, that woe will be now unto <hi>England,</hi> ſince <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> is King. This is the Legend or Story.</p>
            <p>To it I would ſay but this; <hi>What if it be meerely</hi> (as other Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends) forged, and the wandring Knight not to be found to ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie it? Or what, (in caſe there be any truth in the Tale) <hi>if the Knight wanted his Spectacles,</hi> and read OLIVER <hi>instead of</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIVE, or <hi>the Olivet,</hi> for it is in the Apologue of Trees, as the Tale confeſſeth; or what if it were <hi>Oliver</hi> indeed, who <hi>will un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to prove the Poet an authenticke Prophet?</hi> Finally, <hi>what if the Poet ſhould ſpeake</hi> (as ſome of the Heathen Oracles) <hi>truth at una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares?</hi> And ſhould predict, That when <hi>Oliver</hi> ſhould be King, that is, in <hi>Jothams</hi> phraſe, <hi>Judge</hi> (for the Apologue was in the dayes of the Judges) <hi>then woe to us,</hi> i. e. <hi>Cathedrals, Painting and Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> too? would there be any great woe to Chriſtians, to ſee (now <hi>Oliver</hi> is Judge, or Protector) the ruine of Cathedrals, ſince they are of little uſe, and of ſo great offence?</p>
            <p>I will trouble my ſelfe no further with theſe or the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, or ſurmiſes, but let me intreat (thee Reader) to conſider ſeriouſly for thine owne ſatisfaction if thou doubteſt, or for mine if I erre (for I would willingly be convinced) <hi>whether or no any who feare God, who are the Children of the Promiſes, and who converſe with, and waite for the fulfilling of Propheſies; I ſay, whether any of thoſe have juſt cauſe to murmure, repine, or oppugne the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, upon this turne and change?</hi> much leſſe, <hi>whether they have cauſe to reſolve at laſt only to acquieſce, and ſit ſtill, and to gratifie the old and common enemy, which as much as poſſible they can wiſh, viz. to reſolve to ſtand NE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TRALS,</hi> and <hi>let all oppoſe or prevaile that can,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118160:9"/>and dare againſt this preſent power;</hi> which becauſe it was not <hi>a Childe</hi> of <hi>their conception,</hi> they are willing to let periſh by the power of an open and profeſſed enemy, withall putting to their helping or preferring hands; I will ſay no more, but reſerve the reſt for thoughts and ſighs in ſecret.</p>
            <p>Only for a Cuſhion, I will ſuppoſe it poſſible for this paper at one time or other to lye at the Lord Protectors feet, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I wil preſume upon <hi>his low Spirit</hi> in his <hi>High place,</hi> to beſpeake him thus: My Lord, you have but little leaſure, and I but little ability for many words, yet I beſeech you of your clemency to heare me a few.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>You have much power, and are in a great place, but power and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency are ſlippery places, and expoſe to great falls if one be not cautious.</hi> The firſt perſon of your place and power came to a ſad end, not I thinke really for any default of his, but by the malice and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of his corrival; you have many enemies, men of much ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and not of ſimple ſlothfull ſpirits; Beware what you doe, you have a Councel, to adviſe with whom wil be ſafety, <hi>the more you act joyntly with them, the leſſe danger will be to your ſelfe, or the Common-wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>You have Honours to conferre, but be ſure you honour none but ſuch as honour God.</hi> It is but an unwiſe, and a derided work to guild a rotten poſt; and to conferre Honour upon ſinful, ſordid, or unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Perſons, will have but little of Prudence, and leſſe of Piety in it; <hi>ſuch as are precious in Gods ſight, let them be honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and doe you love them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>You have many eyes upon you, ſome expecting, ſome ſuſpecting; diſappoint not the one, neither doe any thing to ſtrengthen the other.</hi> There are who <hi>ſuſpect</hi> you'le KING it, and procure your Heire to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed you; but diſ-appoint thoſe men in their malice, who will thereupon <hi>cry,</hi> and ſtrive to <hi>downe with you, downe with you, even to the ground.</hi> Aske your Councel, whether it were not good pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and preventing policy, to <hi>provide againſt the Family of any Protector, as well as the Family of the late King; and conſider, if an addition were made to the age of the Protector that may be choſen, it would not be better.</hi> Certainly they of <hi>Venice</hi> finde it advantagious that their <hi>Dukes are old;</hi> and with ancient, above forty one, wil be more wiſdome, then with the young though twenty one. The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118160:10"/>elder the Protector is, he wil be the more fitter to doe men good, he will be the unfitter to doe men hurt. By this (if your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhal thinke it meet to endeavour) you will fruſtrate your enemies, and refute the greateſt of their calumnies, and ſurmiſes, and hereby you wil ſatisfie many of your cordial friends, who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect choyſe things from you, and ſuch as accompany holineſſe, humility, and ſelf-denial.</p>
            <p>Finally, <hi>remember while you ſtudy to be a terrour to evil doers, you ſtrive to be an incourager and Protector of thoſe who doe well;</hi> do your utmoſt to pull up <hi>every weed,</hi> but be cautious you pull up no <hi>good Plant</hi> therewith. While you are zealous againſt a Superſtitious, prophane, ignorant, carnal Miniſtry (in which zeale ride on and proſper) be careful, and diligent to perpetuate and incourage an holy, ſpiritual, able, and peaceable company of Preachers, who may advance holineſſe and godlineſſe, and prevent prophanenes and barbariſme, which begins to put forth their monſtrous heads in divers corners of the Land.</p>
            <p>My Lord, ile ſay no more but this; <hi>You are in as much need of help from God now as ever,</hi> indeed more; your work as <hi>Generall</hi> is not yet at an end. I am much inclined to thinke, that at leaſt once more, you wil be forced to draw your Sword againe, and to be a <hi>Deliverer</hi> to this Nation (and thoſe of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> united now to it) which if it fall out according to my prayers and hopes; you wil thereby confirme your ſelfe of right to be our <hi>Judge,</hi> and I pray God ſo to guide you in this your new Honour and Office, as that we may have as good, and great a ground to admire, and bleſſe God for you as a <hi>Protector,</hi> as (your enemies themſelves being witneſſe) we have had to acknowledge you as our <hi>Generall.</hi> And the ſame Lord ſo bleſſe your <hi>preſent Councill.</hi> (made up of men who are deſervedly eſteemed wiſe and godly) and eſpecially ſo diſpoſe of the <hi>Parliament to be,</hi> as that upon your and their account, we may have a good ground to ſay, <hi>God hath reſtored his Judges as at the firſt, and his Counſellours as at the beginning,</hi> that therefore hereafter we may call <hi>Englands Triple-Common-wealth,</hi> THE CITY OF RIGHTEOVSNES, THE FAITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FVL CITY.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
